without further ado I wanna welcome
Danish man burger I think and if there
was one person where people were most
people here were like we need Danish
from Iran or we need a specific present
and then it was really use I'm super
super happy that that then are you
coming on and and and gracing us with
your sense making ability and today
income there's a lot to cover I'm not
pretending that we can cover everything
in an hour but I'm hoping that we can at
least scratch the surface and point
people in the right directions if they
want to follow up and yeah I am hoping
that I think initially when we spoke we
were thinking of taking this kind of all
matter and talk about the generator
function of X was and and and and I'm
kind of like what are the I guess like
more abstract and long-term consequences
from this but I think in the interest of
time we have decided to kind of like you
pick us up where we are right now now
kind of like what are the threads that
we should be unraveling more and then we
see kind of like how that affects much
of the generator functions of extension
is that you're so worried about so thank
you so so much for for coming on today
and it's such a pleasure to have you
here I think you can amuse yourself
whenever you want to as a co-host thank
you so so much for joining I would love
for you to maybe and I'm like to us in
by just kind of like taking us on a tour
of you know what our kind of current
developments where we're not paying
enough attention to and where the
conversation maybe not paying enough
attention to it and it may have major
implications down the line that we
shouldn't be missing right now
Thank You Alison for inviting me here
this is my first of these to join even
though a number of the people that
you've had on before people I respect
and our friends and colleagues I
actually just want to acknowledge first
what an awesome thing you're doing here
I look at the list of people that you've
had on in the last 10 weeks and only 10
percent of these people are here for the
first time it's really kind of an
incredible online university and a good
use of this time so that's really neat
because I haven't been in the previous
ones in the poll said people were
feeling generally better many of them
and you were talking about existential
hope and making opportunities can you
just kind of clue me in briefly what
some of the major themes of the kovat
related make things better opportunities
are that this group has been following
yes okay so there's close out the hive
mind which is kind of like the
incredible opportunities that are
currently popping up for health
extension right because suddenly the
whole world is worried about about their
health and a lot of the current biotech
sector money there was already kind of
like available beforehand is really like
funneled into vaccines that put about
some of the efforts that's on the one
end you know a lot of people out of work
and that kind of that that may slow
innovation Donovan on quite
significantly then I think on the other
hand what we talked about fuses into the
promises of the virtual world right we
have everything from healer medicine in
India to kind like this you know really
kind of like flourishing of global
online universities and such that may
kind of like actually make it much
harder for the general monopolies of the
kind of kind of broken educational
systems that rely on like you know a lot
of foreign for foreign student payments
to survive it may make it much much
harder for them to provide still have
this almost like predatory and hinge on
the system so it was a lot of like what
I want to use in the virtual space are
possible right now
that VR is almost becoming as good as a
human you can as a brain computer
interface and then you know we also
talked about like the different ways of
in which culture shifting in which
people are now like me stepping up and
really fantastic ways in which people
are times like willing to tap into grey
zones and legal areas to save lives
in which people are like stepping up and
proposing you go defense funds for those
you know who are in those gray areas and
saving lives for those people who are
blowing the whistle and in the sense in
which vaguely centralized communities
are coming together and a few
technologies that may help us do that
much much better in the future and
especially from from crypto Commerce and
but then also how many of those
technologies are currently being have
been exploited by more totalitarian
forms of government and all the ways in
which like you know it's a more
predatory state like seeking the nooks
and crannies and which to expand their
power into it
right and so we are usually economic
always the risk and opportunities in
those area and I mean then we last week
we would focus more on the kind of
global scale and in the ways in which
currently you know we have a ton of
people that are really really good at
sense making we have a ton of people
that are really good at modeling
meticulous FHI they all came out
fantastic modeling efforts but it's just
so happens that no one's really
listening we have really good prediction
tools already people working on them but
it still kind of feels that they're not
really effectively informing action yet
but you know there are a few ways like
you know we talked about Dow democracy
about future keys and so on but but
they're just not really entering the
mainstream discourse so like my main
fear is that there are actually a lot of
opportunities available and but a lot of
those people like I think many of us as
they're thinking along those lines are
just not being insulted so I'm one one
kind of choice at me because you have
this in either but there's kind of a
parallel operating system and hope that
we can take over and take over the
system is taking effect
or we can try to try to reform but but
it just doesn't need to make there as
much opportunity to bail in right now
so those are I guess a few things that
we've been talking about I can go on the
laundry list but then I think I would be
running the salon I definitely don't
want to be doing that I get it we can't
meet in person can we meet online and
are there unique opportunities to being
able to meet online if healthcare is
fucked up can we use it to reform
healthcare writ large if education gets
totally disrupted rather than have you
know just a generation that has major
gaps in their education can we reform
education I would like a classic example
right now is the food supply chain is
we've basically by stopping travel to be
stopped the movement of the virus we
also stop the movement of fertilizers
and pesticides and key supply chain
dynamics that have led to this massive
culling of animals and throwing dairy
away and tilling food back into the soil
so we have basically excessive supply
that can't get where it needs so it's
getting ruined while the demand hasn't
actually gone down it's just we can't
route it you know properly and the
perishability and the thin margins are
such that we're actually driving hunger
at scale so the food supply system for
give or take two billion people just got
fucked and so then we're like okay well
having a supply chain that has that many
steps of vulnerability and it isn't a
good idea so if we have to fix it right
now and we do because otherwise tens of
millions or hundreds of millions of
people don't go hungry peacefully right
so you start to get a movement from a
virus to broken supply chains to hunger
to violence to war escalation so let's
say we're looking at the fact that
Nigeria has the largest food insecurity
population and population density in the
world 26 million give or take people
without food security and that their
food system just got completely damaged
and what happened here plus their
economy because they're there based on
the price of oil right like almost their
entire economy is based on the price of
oil which just had this massive Saudi
Arabia Russia oil shock kind of thing
and you look at what that starts to look
like in terms of both so
you know Boko Haram is increasing and
local gangs are increasing and and then
insurgency movements so do we start to
see a massive exit a serious style from
Nigeria
well after Syria and the damage that
happened to the EU where do those people
go because you doesn't want to take them
right and it's under such massive
fracture pressures already after brexit
and after kovat that some places take
them and others don't what does that do
kind of for fracture pressure so so this
is when you can start to see how like a
cascade of events like this goes we take
the damage to the food supply that's
happened in India India and Bangladesh
are particularly interesting because of
the population density multiplied by
total population that is near food
vulnerabilities and so you start to get
a damage to the food supply system they
are and the total number of people that
can be affected is just unprecedented is
astronomical and we were looking at this
before Co vid from climate change so
remember the year started off with
Australia burning right and Wow there
were a number of factors there was an
environmental mismanagement that led to
too much downed wood because they had
prevented small fires and not dealt with
the forestry well and because
groundwater had been used up
irresponsibly in whatever there were a
number of factors but increased dryness
and heat was one of the major factors so
then we started looking at climate
change mediated not just do we have a
climate that takes out the ability for
people to live as a whole which we're
not going to get which is why Caesar and
FHI whatever don't look at climate
change that much but they should when
they factor cascade effects which is do
you have a climate dynamic that leads to
like for instance this upcoming summer
in India and Bangladesh are estimated to
have 52 Celsius heat waves independent
of kovat well that is enough to actually
destroy most of their staple crops and
so when you don't have food stores
singing meaningful enough food stores
you can destroy the staple crops and you
have people that are right on the edge
of basic needs being unmet then what
happened so then do the people in like
without groundwater
and without food and 52 Celsius heat
just die peacefully right or do they
start to try to get access to the
limited resources and then violence
emerges over limited resources so where
do those violence lines cleave along
well they cleave along existing tension
lines so does that look like Hindu
Muslim tension lines sure and so then
does that look like India Pakistan
tension it starts to mount and you start
to see the Cascade that happens when you
have systemic fragility of this kind so
now we still have that upcoming set of
heat waves to deal with in India on top
of the fact that we already just had a
unanticipated crop failure ahead of that
okay so now we're talking about how do
we rebuild things does anybody want to
rebuild this food supply system the way
that it is like no it's the most fucking
terrible thing you can imagine right
because if you're gonna do factory
farming nobody wants that near them
because it's gruesome right it's
environmentally gruesome it's ethically
gruesome it's like nobody wants those
jobs they have to usually be the jobs or
largely run by immigrants who have no
other option and so if you're gonna do
gruesome factory farms and they have to
be in the areas that will accept them
then you have to ship them to far
distances then you also have to have a
very fragile supply chain that can break
from something like COBIT so let's say
we want to make our supply chains less
fragile that also means we want to
increase locality if you want to
increase locality you have to have types
of Agriculture that people are okay
seeing which is actually really good
right because the ability to ship the
horror somewhere else right the open-pit
mining or the mountaintop removal mining
or the factory farm or the landfill that
we can ship the horse somewhere else but
nobody has to see it depend on lots of
shipping and everybody thinks that life
is pretty cool around here because we
put all the ugly parts somewhere else
that is actually one of the things that
drives systemic fragility so if we start
saying well how do we increase food
security well one aspect is can we start
increasing locality in food systems well
doing that will also require making food
systems that are better for soil better
for animal welfare better for the
environment better for human health on
and on right
so and better for preventing future
zoonotic pandemics that occur in places
where you have a bunch of sick animals
in a tight environment so it's important
to remember that right before China had
you know SARS co2 emerged they had to
kill a humungous percentage of all their
pigs because of a swine flu that emerged
because of terrible pork bass factory
farming and and they had another major
bird flu outbreak India had a bird flu
outbreak because factory farms are
terrible and they shouldn't exist so
that's an example of something that just
broke that we have to rebuild because
the consequence of not rebuilding it is
too destructive for the world and we
need to rebuild it differently there's a
bunch of other examples like this so
pretty much the way I see kovat is that
it was just a large enough global issue
to set off the cascade effects of
systemic fragilities that would have
been set off by something and so now the
major issues that we're looking at are
we you know like let's say we look at so
we just talk about food supply let's say
we look at the economy well we already
had a situation with a percentage of
global GDP that went to debt servicing
was so high that the economy was
fundamentally dead and broken right and
we needed to restructure it in some deep
way because you can't have that much of
total GDP going to debt servicing well
as a result of kovat GDP dropped
everywhere and that went way the fuck up
and we were already at an existential
level of GDP to debt ratio so it's like
okay so what what are the economic
effects of trying to keep propping that
system up and if you play them out
they're terrible what does it take to
fix it can we actually redo global
financial monetary policy central
banking policy what is the biggest type
of step we could actually make in this
place
I think it's important to note you know
you were mentioning something that might
be able to decrease predatory
opportunism in in certain places like we
were at education I would say since Cove
it has been happening predatory
opportunism has increased more than I
have ever seen it in any other time or
that I can think of in history because
when the market gets more volatile
there's a lot more money to be made if
you know how to make it there's a lot
more money to be lost there's also a lot
more money to be made because there's
more movement occurring so if you're the
one that is at the top of the power-law
distribution of intelligence and ability
to actuate then you're going to do very
well and we saw that right we saw some
people get stupidly rich during the
Great Depression relative to everyone
else and also get more total asymmetry
of wealth as if most people were getting
poorer so it's a the volatility
increases asymmetries so when you look
at all the private intelligence
companies that when people leave CIA and
NSA and whatever that's where they go to
work with those capabilities who
contracts them who are their main
customers well it's financial
institutions are the biggest customer
there's plenty of other ones right but
hedge funds and private equity funds
whatever so in terms of who was getting
briefings in December and then early
January this is why you saw senators
selling stock in January regarding oh
this is actually a big fucking deal and
this is going to affect the world if I
run a hedge fund and the market is near
the top of what the market has ever been
at and can't keep going like that
forever and I see that there's about to
be a major set of hits even if I
hypothetically have a lot of money and a
lot of power and a lot of access and I
could try to use that to get the c-d-c
in the w-h-o to do the right thing to
save a lot of lives that's not my job
and it's not what my incentive is my
incentive is to say fuck this is the
time to sell all my stocks at the top of
the market I'm gonna get a rebuy them at
the bottom of the market when they are
radically decreased in price and
consolidate the fuck out of the total
power base I'm also gonna short the
market on the entire way down I'm gonna
start shorting Airlines and whatever
else it is and because of
asymmetric information asymmetric
intelligence I'm gonna know about oil
shock issues and food chalk issues and
whatever to be able to know which
commodities to short and which ones to
put options on ahead of time then there
were a lot of pools of capital like
sovereign wealth funds and family
offices that big pools of liquid capital
that could not be well deployed recently
because we had negative interest rates
on bonds and so it's like I can't just
leave my money sitting somewhere and
have it make money and negative interest
rates are because the market was so
broken because so much of the money was
going to debt servicing and the global
wealth inequality was so much that you
had to basically just keep pumping free
money which is what negative interest is
to keep the system from collapsing and
so and you didn't have very high
volatility so now those huge pools of
sovereign wealth and you know liquid
capital are like awesome we get a buy up
infrastructure for pennies on the dime
right and consolidate power law so the
people who have most access to
intelligence and actuation capacity have
been busier than ever during this time
not relaxing right if you're if you have
less to do you know that you are not at
the power law distribution at the top of
the power law distribution because those
people are seeing this as a maximum
opportunity space but it's the
opportunity to be able to say oh you
know lots of volatility and it's not
just volatility in markets it's also
awesome this is a great way to roll out
the surveillance tech we were wanting to
roll out to get all of that data for
surveillance capitalism or to increase
the power of states if that's our
particular thing to do so that's and now
people will go for it right or we can at
least force it through or situations
where people won't be able to tend to
elections in the same way they would
have previously been able to because of
health issues is a great time to try and
manipulate elections so or if I'm China
and I'm trying to advance the belt and
Road initiative and there were some
sticky places that weren't moving
through and it happens to be that I'm
really
only manufacture PPE at decent scale in
the world the places that wouldn't sign
the belt and road initiative before well
now if that's the only way that they get
to not die of the plague is that we come
help them out and also not die of
poverty as their economy crashes or
let's say that we're Russia wanting to
get the Eastern Alliance Baltic state
back and kind of weaken NATO forces in
EU or so just kind of you could think
about all the power players they're all
motivated to do the shit they were
already doing but where you have during
the equilibrio phase it's much harder to
change the total relative power during
that time where you break up the
equilibrium you can have much more
radical changes of power coming out the
other side like you know think about the
u.s. coming out clearly the world leader
of world war ii not going in that
position and britain coming out
radically downregulated everyone who is
sophisticated in the game of power is
seeing this as that type of thing and so
I would say the fragility has set off
like we have increased meaningfully
increased risk of violence in the US and
in other developed areas at the social
level of just how many people are are
freaked out right like they have very
partial sense making in a world
dominated by a narrative warfare and
information warfare so nobody feels like
they can actually make real sense so
they just do tribalism stuff and so
they're and it's tricky right so they
see I'm a right oriented person
I don't know particular people that have
died but I also live in a low population
density area and everything on the news
is totally suspect as fake news and I'm
afraid of the idea that the the
corruption and conspiracy and whatever
would be happening to control things and
actually go down and look at my local
hospital and there's nobody fucking
there and it's empty and I see a few
other things of like empty hospitals no
of course if you actually have a
pandemic going on you will try to stop
elective processes and so you will have
doctors going out of business and empty
hospitals while also having a real
pandemic but there's some sophistication
and nuance to be able to make sense of
that whole thing and if I don't have it
partial perspective is pretty compelling
right so then I'm like oh fuck they're
trying to take our freedoms away we
founded this country based on the right
to bear arms and you know stand up
against our government so that thing
starts to happen right and and then you
see simultaneous to that black guy
running gets shot protests happens a
bunch of bunch of black people doing a
protest carrying guns right and so you
see the like oh there's lots of sides
that are at meaningful tension with each
other increasing the signaling of
violence then we see the actual violence
increasing in in certain areas riots
that happened in London and whatever and
then very meaningful stuff in places
like Nigeria and then we see bigger
things like I don't think most people
pay enough attention but when you look
at general McChrystal coming out a few
weeks ago saying I'm gonna be using
advanced DARPA technology to counter the
fake news that Trump is putting out
people should pay attention when a
four-star general who ran covert ops for
the US military whose job was to
overthrow governments from the inside
using tools of narrative warfare he
talks about using advanced AI semantic
capability developed by DARPA to go
against the standing president like that
should be a signal if you were paying
attention oh what the fuck that is
closer to Civil War I don't know what
signals are closer right so you just
start looking at all those types of
things and you look at the increased
attention and signaling regarding
militarism between US and China and on
and on so we could go by sector whether
we talk about the financial sector the
economic sector movements towards
violence grid security and say the
existing risks that were there just got
accelerated by like a decade in almost
all areas I mean now the question is to
come out the other side not way way WAY
worse requires dealing with all that not
just dealing with the virus but dealing
with the second and third order effects
that have already kicked off and if we
don't deal with that we will come out
way way worse in order to deal with it
we have to do deep enough changes that
we will
say hey we don't want to redo food
supply this way or monetary policy this
way and we could come out much better
but that requires that the people who
are thinking about how to do it better
have to be as effective at making shit
happen at a global scale as the groups
that are currently working on power
consolidation
yeah I think yeah man there are so many
things like I mean one of the things
just like you know I think echoing would
like living off a few of the things that
that you mentioned one of the things was
like being the Belton vote initiative
right like I think in a previous podcast
somebody mentioned what what if China
was actually tying that you know kind of
like to the you know to the to the
condition of using their digital
currency right then like many of the
kind of like digital currencies and like
of the promises of freedom that were
excited about of them previously would
kind of like fall to the wayside then
right and I think the same is true when
when you look at like I mean if I look
on if I think back of how this all
started and how can I try optimistic I
was that there's a ton of opportunities
to do an incredible amount of good and
we've been thinking about this and I
think really really smart people are on
it and I think about it and I talking
about it but meanwhile like if I
actually look at what's happening in the
world in the meantime it seems like
things are just slowly getting worse and
worse a little bit like on a very kind
of like in a personal level like I was
out in San Francisco a few days ago and
like they were like Street conic car
races on the street right like people
with motorcycles with cars racing out
like multiple people's like peeing in
the park
he's totally overwhelmed like police
every every 5 meters wherever I went
like people just like totally wasted
everywhere on the street and I was like
wow this is very different to like the
types of worlds that we're thinking
about on a daily basis and those global
sell-off so you know it's kind of like
weird to see that Delta between
meanwhile like it's kind of painful to
see like we are always thinking and in
in ways in which the system could be
much better but like it
adjustment like we're not taking into
account many of the kind of like just
very real physical kind of like physical
constraints that are like that are kind
of corny and making people move right
and I feel like the same is true like on
you know if we think about it on a
global scale in terms of and what what
may not happen with oil like one of the
things that we've been talking about is
that on the one and it's it's somewhat
grade that all futures are negative
because for ones we may be able to make
them
move to like we knew and energy but on
the other hand also totally fucking
terrifying right because that may mean
like much much more likely that we enter
into like final conflict between
different powers and especially with the
US couldn t realize it doesn't have a
chip in order on a global scale right
like we've never seen connect like
nations convict in international water
moving peacefully or like switching
peacefully right so it's like it's just
seems like it's a total weird cognitive
dissonance by which you can dream up was
really amazing changes that could be
occurring meanwhile things are moving
really quickly in all sorts of
directions and in really complicated
ways with not only second-order effects
but like that's why I mentioned the
currency like the you know potentially
Chinese kind of like maybe are ordering
something like you know that digital
currency if they ever kind of like
enforcing they like the development both
on many others that's on the second
order that's almost like a third order
effect so I my question so it's a
long-winded way of saying there's it
seems to be a ton of opportunity this
needs to be a ton of risk it seems like
we have really smart people together
often and I'm also speaking about your
circles they're thinking really well
about this and you just mentioned how
intelligent people within the system are
gaining could make a ton of money by
gaming the system with the information
that they have so what is kind of like
the kinds of information that we could
be using and the kinds of kind of a
comparative advantage that we may have
in putting that to the table to create a
better world or not the worst ones of
those
something I was personally really
impressed with and I don't mean in a
good way just impressed upon me when I
first started encountering the halls of
power in the world more so top of
government and the finance and like that
is
how few people there were actually
really good thinkers they were smart
enough to understand how to execute
certain types of things not particularly
creative not particularly systemic not
particularly critical but like just
basically smart enough they were mostly
ambitious like super fucking ambitious
and super hard-working and slanted
heavily in the cluster B Direction
cluster B meaning dsm-5 personality
disorder specifically the power seeking
ones that are willing because like if
you don't have something psychologically
wrong with you for the most part those
are really miserable lives to be
continuously engaging with people that
are trying to fuck you over and stab you
in the back and lied to you so that you
can just get more power that doesn't
equate to a meaningful quality of life
and have no real relationships because
the only people that are interacting
with you want something from you like
you there has to be something mostly
psychologically wrong with you to want
to gain a lot of power so the
psychological dispositions that are
power seeking you call it sociopathy
psychopathy narcissism tend to be
willing to put up with the difficulties
and do the fucked up things necessary to
win a lot of win-lose games and get to
the top of the power law distribution of
power systems
and sometimes you actually need to not
have complex thoughts so that you can
avoid looking at the externalities
you're causing and that you can give
plausible deniability even to yourself
and to be able to just execute on some
simple things which is usually where
more power comes from so then I see
people who care more and have more
complex thinking not want to do things
that will cause lots of externalities
and think about what the quality of life
in their short period of time being
alive is and not necessarily want to be
engaged in those types of financial
warfare and political warfare whatever
all the time and so they just don't ever
get much power which also means they
don't influence things very much so
basically there is a disposition there
is a systemic disposition that makes
sociopaths and they're like mostly run
the world and until we actually fix that
we are just on a movement towards self
induced determination I mean like you
know why the worst rise to the top and
and and all of like all of those
arguments that I think I usually really
you know arguments against the
consolidation of power Lloyd and I think
that you've in previous podcast and I
mean you're writing on it a lot of
connect systems that are not currently
being built and the crypto commerce base
in which at least you could have better
sense making tools that and I would make
it would make those kind of tendencies
much harder but you know I wonder
whether you know you're proposing that
like should we reform or should we exit
and build new
one that speak orthogonal to that
question first just addressing that
question I would say there's there's
roughly three horizons of focus that I
pay attention to I pay attention to like
immediate triage which isn't trying to
reform the current systems and it isn't
trying to build new ones it's just
trying to keep some terrible shit from
happening that we can't fix afterwards
and so like how do we prevent massive
death in India right now and massive
escalation of violence
we're not even we're not gonna fix
capitalism or fix corruption or we'll
fix the current Indian government to do
that it's like can we can we do the
right things with supply chains and hade
and shit to be able to prevent because
there are some issues that you can
prevent but you can't fix them after
they've happened they they are
irreversibly destructive and so one of
the things I'm very focused on is the
kind of sense making that shows us the
escalation pathways to various types of
irreversible catastrophic risk so that
we can identify the most targeted
interventions to stop those things from
happening so that's actually neither
fixing the current systems nor making
better ones right that's just keep the
patient from bleeding out then there is
how do we work with the current
institutions to make them better because
we're not gonna have post capitalist
post nation-state post democratic
societies running the world in the next
few years or just there's no fucking way
that's gonna happen and it's not even
gonna happen in the generation their
generational shift has to occur for the
up leveling of systemic sense making and
for good systems that start to happen
somewhere to get through the resistance
necessary to be the primary operating
system so that means that the you know
fifty to a hundred trillion dollars that
trades hands every day that is that much
collective human incentive in human
behavior is going to keep running
through the systems it's running through
for a while so we have to take those
systems and make them less terrible not
even say more good just less terrible
and that's kind of the second horizon of
focus is institutional repair
how do we take and most of the
institution's we currently have were
better when they were created and then
they decayed because predatory
opportunism kind of decayed them and
that's actually if you you know Sam Oh
probably spoke about that when he was on
here Michael Vassar might have the
theory of Institutional decayed
civilizational decay so if we look at
the way that the American Republic was
initially intended it would it's it's
not a perfect form of governance and it
of course doesn't address how to deal
with a decentralized exponential tech
world and and Facebook like it doesn't
they weren't thinking about those issues
so we need something better than that
but it's so many thousands of times
better than the shit we have right now
that is basically like a maximally
corrupt kleptocracy pretending to be a
republic and not even pretending all
that much because it doesn't matter what
people think cuz they don't do anything
which was very clear in things like the
Epstein case or even Co vid right now
but Epstein case was very interesting to
me because that marked the hallmark in
my witnessing in the US where some
people still believed in the news to
where nobody actually believed in the
news if they were paying attention
because when Epstein died all of the
major publications whether they were
believed to be right leaning or left
leaning their major publications
continuously and only said when Epstein
commits suicide in prison and I just
don't know anyone that actually thinks
that he commits suicide in prison and so
what that meant was everyone said hmm
what what the fuck is that if the left
and the right leaning and supposedly
owned by different people and different
organizations and they're all saying
something that nobody believes and then
but still nobody does shit about it
because nobody thinks they can do
anything about it and they're all on
benzos and opiates and porn and Facebook
so the they're kind of too weakened and
addicted to do anything anyways plus if
you think about trying to go do
something about it you're like okay
don't revolutions require violence the
SWAT team has tanks like what the fuck
do we do against tanks so how do you
deal with these things when it seems
like there
things are actually relatively
comfortable and no matter how upset I
get by the time I've scrolled Facebook
for five minutes I forgot right like the
hyper normal stimulus is strong enough
that I forgot and the seeming chance of
succeeding at something seems so hard
that people just it doesn't really
matter so we don't even have to pretend
that there is a republic that much
anymore on the epstein thing it's
important to just kind of say here
people who paid attention there said
okay wait so mueller said when he was
trying him the first time said publicly
I was told to shut this case down that
he's a epstein as a US intelligence
asset that's above my pay grade okay
and then we find out the things Epstein
was involved in and we and then we hear
the names it would be part of the court
investigation if it went the next day
which involves presidents on both the
Republican and Democrat side let lots of
other people say so this is the most
important court case in the history of
the US where multiple presidents on both
sides and you know people of all kinds
of power are possibly going to be
indicted for like some of the worst
crimes people can think about and the
dude dies in jail on suicide watch and
the cameras go off and everything the
day before we're like okay wait does
that mean that the there isn't really a
justice system and the there isn't
really a police system as part of a
justice system and there isn't really
news and the intelligence agencies are
part of are involved in things that
involve like child sex trafficking
anyone who's paying attention had all
those thoughts and then just started do
another shit again so
the topic that comes up for me here is
what does it take to think about better
systems and solutions but then what does
it take to go implement them and to be
as effective at implementing as okay if
I want to protect the rainforests in
South America I have to be more
effective than the multinationals and
the national interests behind trying to
cut the rainforests down which is the
CCP major Chinese multinationals
European multinationals some Kremlin
forces from super corrupt politicians
doing all those types of things
we lose the fucking Amazon if it
continues to be some very incompetent
NGOs against those forces so if you want
to actually keep it you actually have to
be able to out influence them and that's
one of the things that I'm really
wanting to see is typically people only
start to engage in the game of influence
which is also the game of power if they
are oriented towards power seeking in
ways that makes them not good stewards
of power and the world is fucked from
this for people who are trustworthy who
could be good stewards of power of
groups who could be they will not for
their own intrinsic reasons be oriented
to want to do that but the ones who
could for the collective good be willing
to step up into that shitty life of
engaging in the game of power because
it's actually good for the whole that is
one of the critical things that is
needed for the world to make you right
now and that's neither new systems oh so
I went off that's neither like there's
triage work there's fix the existing
systems there's making new better
systems but all of them require being
able to move stuff effectively at a
global scale yeah I think one thing you
know like one thing about the sense
making my parrot is like if you make an
elephant in the brain when Henson kind
of points out - why can like his work on
predictions why he thinks said it has
never been picked up and it's basically
like people don't want to know what's
going to happen because that means that
people could have predicted wrong which
means you can hold people accountable
for having predicted wrong and firing
made wrong decisions and people don't
want that they just want to corrected
you treat themselves and say no to each
other
trying to do the best but meanwhile no
one actually really cares whether
anything like were there anything gets
done and like and I do worry you know
that even if we had pretty good since
making a purchase is like you know
maitake ism and a few other tools
already out there that are really quite
fantastic but they seem to not be
coupled to actuators right and and you
could say well either we can't wake up
the establishment so that they you
should be using something like a few
jerky vgm a few degree government system
or we try to kind of like do better
ourselves which you know then again
comes to the point of like who's willing
to step out within our communities to
kind of like looking forward and do that
you know and then and I think actually
mean well I mean you know just I think
it came out today or yesterday or
something right like Twitter and
Facebook just like now cooperating with
CDC and was a WH or something to and to
try to make sense of like fake news
posts about about covert 19 which then
tricks people and having their sickness
trust and any type of sense making
apparatus anymore that's kind of like
vaguely in the mainstream right and and
people just getting more and more down
the conspiracy alley because you know as
you said within the Epstein case like it
doesn't really seem like anyone can be
trusted anymore and w John another like
you know organs are telling you like one
day don't wear masks the next day
totally wear masks and like it's all so
confusing it's really really hard to
come back figure out who to trust but I
do actually think that this community
has this intrinsic benefit of like being
able to have have called the shots
really really early and so you know I
just want to kind of like maybe poke a
little bit more on that
you know what would it you already
saying well it is almost a property of
those people who should step up to do
something that they inherently don't
want to and and and that those who want
to may not be the right people who
should we should do it so how do you
incentivize those people if at all or
like you know what I specific kind of
like projects that you think could
require a leader right now do you think
would be good people to take something
on like you know if you're talking quite
locally in quite actionable like what
what would you like people and this
community you focus on more and then you
know maybe we can outsource it amongst
ourselves and take them on
I would be very in heartened if the
rationalists community and EA community
started to use words like sacred and
devotion more and not as a kind of it
intellectually makes sense that there is
a thing that we can define this way
semantically and or it's a signal II
kind of thing but from having
experiences of and I don't mean to
define them in some kind of pre rational
religious way but sacred what is most
precious what is most meaningful to me
and what is meaningful to me more than
my own experience in my own life and why
is my own experience in my own life even
meaningful and what does that tell me
about the value of life and experience
as a whole and then in light of that
what am i what is my devotion to and to
not just what has the best utility
function they move in different parts of
us and you have to do both if you read
the daodejing
as a book of leadership it basically
says in many different ways the person
who really wants to lead everybody
should run away from because there's
something wrong with that guy and
they're probably basically
psychologically a child and the person
who really really doesn't want to lead
and everyone pushes into the position
because everyone trusts them from how
they show up as long as that person
doesn't start to identify with their
world too much they can probably do it
an aria job but you asked how do we kind
of push people there I would say if
people meditate on what is actually
sacred to you what do you want your life
to be in service to you what do you
really understand is going on in the
world right now and let that be more of
what has your attention than your to-do
list or your Facebook feed then they
will start to be a sense of what you
can't not do and it's not just for you
know personal disposition but what the
greater collective need and what's
meaningful calls
- yeah I mean I think you know the
rationalists and I've never been there
but have vesicular saucers for example
right and and I do think that that kind
of like feeling is something that I want
to tap into with existential hope like
is he created this website with that
positive visions for Humanity and like
is more like a philosophy and kind of
like um blog really that I think because
if you if you talk to many people that
have done incredible things they have
done them because they've read very
early very inspiring stuff that never
that they could never forget about right
like it came from this like total kind
of like internal admiration for this
incredible future that that they could
see or for this you know really like an
incredible kind of like almost like
aesthetic flow state or something that
that came from an intrinsically positive
place and I think that's an incredibly
kind of like stable motivator right it
doesn't you know it doesn't make you it
doesn't make you stop very very very
very quickly right and so I think having
that and having that in community I
think is a really motivating force I
would kind of like I'm worried a little
about you know like electing like the
the global leader I think you know one
thing that we also often tend to talk
about in this communities is like well
it took us a really long time in history
to kind of like stop asking who should
be in power but to start asking more
like you know what kinds of
architectures can we create kind of like
which empower more people right so even
there I think you know this kind of like
tendency of electing you know the the
right person you know maybe we can we
can do a little better than that and if
we get the right education is in place
and I'm I'm curious whether you know you
could point to a few specific kind of
like I guess like cooperation
architectures or ways in which you think
people are already cooperating well that
we could model off it seems to me that
you Allison are personally working your
ass off to make these videos available
to everyone that you're personally
taking a bunch of leadership initiative
during this time to make a more
beautiful future that you feel inspired
to do and that you care about and
everybody's wouldn't be here if you
weren't doing that and everyone is
appreciating and they're not all taking
equal leadership and making it happen
don't get confused that decision
architectures to come about still don't
take people taking leadership action and
make them happen like who the fuck
figures out the decision architectures
who implements them who gets people
involved that's always it's like
inspiration on the behalf of some people
that makes those things happen so don't
underweight that that is that can be a
bridge to people saying I'm gonna take
leadership not to hold leadership
forever I'm gonna try and take some
leadership to create things that help
everyone be able to participate in
leadership and more democratized in
better ways and that is the healthy
right kind of leadership the right kind
of leadership is I will use some
asymmetric influence or power in a way
that tries to increase everyone else's
access to be able to do that as well
rather than to continue to increase my
own asymmetry of power over everyone
else that's the what I would call
legitimate versus a legitimate power and
so what I'm proposing is that a
legitimate power has a necessary
function in moving us to a post
illegitimate power or dynamic world are
you going to relaunch the Americans
project and if so please or if not
please could you present the main thesis
thesis slash aims to members of the hive
they're unfamiliar with it Thanks
the emergence project was a name of some
kind of research and aspirations I was
engaged in like a decade ago which is
just part of this ongoing thread for me
of how to understand the nature of the
problems in a way that gives rise to
better solutions and implement them that
was a particular point in time with a
particular set of collaborators and
the work the insights advanced a lot
since then so I wouldn't say relaunch
that I would say that was a step in a
lot of steps for me they were you know I
like I started with activism young and
there were certain problems I really
cared about and then I saw that the
projects working on solving those
problems just moved the problems and
caused other problems and like I very
personally saw that like we worked to
get fences around to preserve for
elephants in Africa but it didn't
address the underlying poverty and basis
of why there were poachers or the
poacher started moving to hunt the
mountain gorillas and the white rhino
both of which were more endangered and
I'm like fuck we just worked super hard
to make the world worse because we just
had more endangered animals get poached
and I started looking at all the places
where that happens I'm like it's pretty
much everything because we we defined
the problems too narrowly and so our
solution to a narrowly defined problem
ends of externalizing harm in other
areas so I started looking at more and
more of the problems how they
interconnected and then are their
underlying generators that give rise to
them and then also how are they are
there things that are getting worse
which got me in the catastrophic and
existential risk and then I'm like man
there's so many fucking catastrophic
risks if we solve the top 10 we'd only
buy like 10 years because there's
thousands of them they're all driven by
the same generator function so we can't
just deal with them all kind of as
instances we have to deal with the whole
class so that led me to thinking about
why do humans use white what is it about
human architecture human behavioral
architectures that has us keep
developing more power and using it badly
and what would it take to be able to not
have us be bad stewards of power
technological power using it badly on
purpose warfare and rivalry and whatever
or using it badly
not on purpose meaning just
externalities but you know they have
cumulative effects in that scale so that
gave rise to this kind of generator
functions of existential risk work and
then thinking about are there
categorical solution
- those generator functions that make a
new civilization model the kernel of a
new civilization those a bunch of years
of work to kind of figure out what are
there and can we define a necessary and
sufficient set of design criteria for a
civilization that can have exponential
tech and not self-terminate we came up
in that research that the answer is yes
that there is actually architectures
that are possible there doesn't mean
we'll get there they're hard but there
are possible things so then there was
how do we work on building that and then
also the next step was well that's gonna
take generations and we don't get there
currently if we don't do a whole bunch
of the you know triage work and working
to change the current institution so
what kind of both intelligence and
influence needs to happen so there's
that's kind of the progression of
interests and projects and emergence
project was one kind of step in that
inquiry I just shared from hoping that
is one of them another let's say data
stage in that in your projection and
maybe I mean it's now 7:00 p.m. so what
we usually do is like people whoever
wants to stay on stay on but now I
always want to give to my panelists like
an easy way to go maybe I mean you super
welcome to stay on and sure there's a
ton of questions but you know maybe as
the final words or as words to lead on
to a nexus fashion and like what are
kind of like things that are currently
on your mind whatever kind of like next
things that you will be focusing your
attention on tomorrow and the days after
and just for context if people go their
civilization emerging as a blog I put up
a few years ago put a few articles on
and then haven't put anything on in
several years and there's like a new
economic series part 1 2 3 4 it was
supposed to be in eight part series so I
described several parts of what's wrong
with economics and then never get around
to finishing explaining what to do with
it because there's other stuff that
became a higher priority there's maybe
still some value and some
most of stuff that I've been focused on
doesn't have a particular public face
because not all projects benefit from a
lot of attention
but there is a project that I'm working
to get over the line that will have a
public face and that I would be very
interested in this community's feedback
on and participation with which is a
basically a site that will be trying to
help correct the information ecology in
the epistemic Commons by doing both
being able to vet the information space
for the information that has highest
confident intervals and most
significance and being able to share
that in the right form so kind of not
news but meta news but then also being
able to show the epistemic process by
which we come to that so people don't
just get better information to do
sense-making but better information
processing capabilities so sometime in
the next month or so beta version of
that should be up and I look forward to
hear people's thoughts on it very cool
yes today we had two models out here one
on Infinity project which is like a
vague way in which we could model the
whole economy and then the other one by
Jaime Jarvis on your own accord 19
argument chains from corcovado to view
and if you guys have connected but maybe
that will be useful some pointed touch
base on as well and you see I want to
yeah oh great okay it's super well I
want to give you the chance to attempt
like to gracefully bow out here and
meanwhile you're also very very well to
stay on I'm sure thank you I'm happy to
hop off people like to talk about things
when the speaker leaves but I'm also
happy to stay and answer questions if
that's desired okay I'm gonna meet you
had a bunch of questions and I think the
last one that you posted yeah that
looked quite good I'm gonna need you now
all right so first of all I'm a big fan
of all the stuff I've been amazed by
your videos and thoughts and so on the
second my question is historically the
entities that gained civilization like
and became super organisms their
religions
and I'm curious if you have any ideas of
how to create anti rivals or game be ich
religion like structures and what
advantages and disadvantages there are
in kind of co-opting or hijacking the
religious aspect of the brain in order
to you know steer a burgeoning
civilization in that way yeah it's
actually really worth studying the
religions that had in some meaningful
endurance and
were less directly violent so studying
the Quakers studying the Jews like
there's some very interesting things
regarding how those collective
intelligence systems worked Jews
specifically being a diaspora not having
a physical location to defend or to be
able to rest upon had to create this
kind of decentralized collective
intelligence system to have synchrony
well-being in embedding cultures so
there's yeah there's a bunch of
interesting things to study there and of
course we can look at the Jains and the
Buddhists and groups that historically
had non-violence as higher principles
and you see that like Tibet can stay
safe for a pretty long time until it
actually becomes a risk and then it gets
taken over by a militaristic force
pretty easily right and so one of the
tricky things has been and this is like
when you look at one of the things that
blows my mind is looking at the history
of Christianity and saying okay so when
we look at the Inquisition or the witch
trials or the Crusades or any of the
things that said they were in Jesus's
name and then you look at the Gospels of
Jesus saying let he who has no sin cast
the first stone like how the fuck did
people figure out that piece of mental
gymnastics to do that thing right so you
start to see an evolution and you can
see like the Essenes went Jane direction
with Christian kind of ideas and then
the Crusades went a different direction
so it's almost like you the religion is
like a mimetic complex and it can
undergo mutation and some of those will
have it propagate more and defend itself
against external forces more typically
those are the ones that move it in the
direction of effective violence not
always often so one of the big questions
becomes how does a peaceful culture stay
peaceful well not being overtaken by
warring cultures medically economically
or military
because if the warring culture is
willing to initiate that thing in the
peaceful culture loses by default then
that doesn't work but if the peaceful
culture to be able to defend itself
against a militarized culture has to
reallocate all of its attention to being
better at warfare than the militarized
culture it's not a peaceful culture
anymore so there is that's a question I
spent a lot of time with and there are
some very interesting insights on that
but that's like a whole that would take
another conversation there's some
graphical so I'm curious if you know are
there less violent militaristic examples
or at least an idea of how to structure
a system that isn't that isolated and
still doesn't involve the militaristic
ethos and so I mentioned the Jews and
then also even the Quakers when they
were say embedded within dominant
Protestant and other religions here in
the US so you have ones that were not
which is different than the Amish who
stayed isolated ones that stay isolated
is one thing but ones that will be
embedded within a dominant culture and
interact with that dominant culture and
even get positions in the halls of power
while being able to maintain fealty to
their relationships is that's actually a
very interesting study and I will say
that none of them I believe are quite
adequate you could take the Masons as
another example right which are quite
interesting similarly and I mean the
Masons mostly after the US was formed so
geographic isolation is obviously one
factor so what religion we could create
on the Mars base is one whole kind of
question but the ones that geographic
proximity is one question which is what
types of rituals require physical
embodiment and the people to be able to
share in that way versus physical
isolation which is which ones require
not being infiltrated
other memes and other people yeah
alright obviously doesn't really answer
the question it just expanded on the
question and it's a really interesting
topic and we would need some more time
yeah I also I quit like a bit Weinstein
thoughts on I with talisman when we
talked about how can we create over
nations from from the current from from
covert 19 you know we're kind of going
through a few of the kind of like
factors that make religions great and
we're trying to kind of like see whether
you can kind of like almost like
modulate movement according to those but
the problem is that you know like
they're really really hard to come back
fake you know like many of the things
that make them work are kind of like
because we've intrinsically buy into
them it's really hard to engineer
movement that has the same properties
even the phrasing of can we utilize or
hijack that set of dispositions in the
brain for some useful purpose isn't what
gives rise to the experience that people
have devotion to right like there is an
actual experience of belonging and
experience of aspiration to ethics and
numinous experience that is an actual
trends and mental operator as opposed to
simply an omniscient operator thinking
about a transcendental operator so it's
a it's a different thing someone doesn't
have to have sloppy metaphysics to be
able to understand phenomenology
Mohammed probably was less Muslim than
why became four generations later
because they were raised in it from
where he on so their phenomenology is
more entangled with the system than
whoever designed the system enrolled
right so we could be the designers if
not the faithful I think it's very
interesting to explore religions that
emerge
from authentic depth of insight and
experience that weren't seeking to be
religions and yet the depth of
experience and insight about the human
condition was meaningful enough and
compelling enough that it had some
organic growth versus ones that were
intended to gain power oftentimes for
political purposes and that were
thinking about how to hijack different
kinds of groupthink and belonging and
superstition and the different
dispositions that those things will take
I think is also another very interesting
angry all right thank you we're gonna
give a few and make the chance for a few
other participants that asking questions
SAS had another question stop on with
you hi
yep yeah I just wondering so Daniel
talks a lot about how you should think
about the problem in depth to make sure
that you don't Weiss implements in
solution you don't cause other
externalities is there is there like a
like a balance to be had between between
how much time you spend thinking about a
problem versus implementing because for
example you can spend your whole life
thinking about something to try to
implements a perfect solution to it but
then in the end you obvious as effective
as if you maybe implements a partial
partial solution then kind of figure
things out along the way yeah so
sometimes the only way to actually
figure out what the externalities are is
to start to experiment or to figure out
how it works is to start to experiment
and but the key is do I need to do safe
to fail probes and safe to fail type
experimental environments and it's gonna
depend upon the degree of consequential
ities like what is the externality
consequence of this thing and what type
of I'll tell you how I think about it
it's what is the complexity in terms of
like total number order of magnitude of
interactions of the situation we're
trying to interact with so let's say I'm
looking at doing some biotech thing in
humans there's going to be a lot more
little complexity of biological
interactions that can occur than if I'm
trying to change something in a computer
chip and so I think about how many what
how many orders of magnitude of
interactions are here and what how many
orders of magnitude if I considered so
that's one thing I'll think about is the
the phase space of likely interactions
relative to what I've thought about and
if that's even within rough powers of 10
I'm at least thinking about it then I
think about as best I can
what are the consequences at least that
are in the second order and maybe some
bit of the third order said that I can
think about and the more consequential
those are also the better we want to
have thought about it and the more we
want to roll it out in a progressive
process so if I'm thinking about oh I
just created some self-replicating
synthetic biology let's release it in
the backyard and see what happens
that's a dumb idea right because the AI
I don't know what the externalities are
gonna be and it could be that I just
released great green goo and it kills
everything do I release it in a certain
kind of bsl-4 laboratory environment to
be able to witness what's happening
right like that would be the the let's
actually find out what it does because
we can't just think about it we have to
experiment and get into the medium
itself now if I'm looking at a
hybridized crop where I just bread a
couple crops together the total amount
of genetic change on that compared to a
genetically modified crop versus
synthetic biology are gonna have me want
to do different degrees of safety
analysis so like when I think about with
kovat and drugs that could help if we
take a drug that's been around for a
really long time like hydroxychloroquine
or methylene blue or ivermectin or
whatever drugs that we've had for 50 or
70 years and used in millions of people
and have a huge amount of long-term
safety data on and now I'm just looking
at are they effective I'm doing efficacy
studies I might be willing to expedite
to speed up that research more than a
new drug that we don't have long term
safety data on
because I might say oh well it didn't
cause any major consequences in the two
months I did the trial but it's because
it's but it might be causing
consequences that have delayed
biological reactions to show up a year
two years later so if I already have
long term data on safety I can do faster
stuff on efficacy so I'm much more
willing as from a policy perspective to
expedite FDA authorization on long term
existing drugs than new ones and I'm
also more willing to expedite drugs than
vaccines because the like a small
molecule drug isn't intended to have an
enduring effect whereas a vaccine is
actually intended to modulate the th1
th2 systems for years or decades or
permanently and so long-term safety
studies are actually more important and
something that I'm anticipating will
have a longer-term effect so that's an
example of like based on how much we
already know that's adjacent and what
basis for concern about risk is there
what degree of appropriate research
would need to come in place um I think
that brings you back to like one
question that I think we almost at the
beginning of this which is you know
given the incredible really failure of
response that we've seen I think in the
US and you know can be how do you best
make sense of that do you think that is
just gaining confidence or do you think
that there's like some something
something more under the hood that many
of us you know like maybe don't don't
like to see it
do I think that everyone who is in a
position of influence has maximally good
motives and that any lack of
effectiveness is simply a result of
incompetence I think that's just silly
when you frame it that way
right do I think that every major
politician and different countries that
are worrying over power grabs and
everyone working in who would benefit
from surveillance tech and who would
benefit from a collapse of the economy
do I think that all the people who have
major influence and could influence
institutional response really just want
to save all the lives they can make
everything as good as they can keep the
market from crashing and you know keep
all the jobs intact and the only reason
we didn't do a better job is just
incompetence I think that's just silly I
think that we have people who are in
positions supposedly on behalf of some
larger thing but there is a conflict of
interest where it's actually on behalf
of whatever their personal interests are
and they're advancing those agendas now
does that mean there is one coordinated
cabal conspiracy at the top no it means
that there is a decentralized
a set of opportunistic power grab
incentives combined with having to do
enough towards the thing they're
supposed to do that they don't get
kicked out of their position and do I
think that there's an even distribution
on how sociopathic everyone is no
there's this is probably a Gaussian
distribution on that but no I think
saying that you know obviously very few
people needed to die from kovat had we
been paying attention in December and
early January and doing effective
responses and we didn't need to fuck the
whole economy in the food supply chains
that need to get damaged did all those
things happen just because all of the
nation states are super bureaucratic and
and the decision-making processes are
slow no that's not the only reason
alright thanks I don't know whether you
read by and Robin Hanson came out with
this post a while ago on Group A and
Group B alliances slowly and basically
making a point that um after this the
economic world order will be largely
defined by those people that by those
countries that have got shit together
and control and those you
Wow
the key lies in
and
thank you even see that between houses
so currently that
right I'm back me we didn't hear me
oh okay that's fine well I was just
gonna say there's a really interesting
article by Robin Hanson where he's
basically talking about group a and
Group B alliances and they're currently
like on a geopolitical scale this is
kind of shifting in the sense where and
many countries that were previously
group and a lines or countries that were
kind of like more high up in the like
geopolitical order are kind of like
moving down because they're not really
not getting their act together and the
u.s. may also moving to into a group B
Alliance for which it may not be safe
enough to be in kind of let's say the
Group A Alliance which can have flow of
Labor and flow of goods amongst
themselves and if that so happen and I
see that kind of like on a on a local
level where you know if you have
different parts of people that all have
different safety standards and somewhat
more and keeping their shit together and
it's working really well um you know
that trans isn't transitive and in the
sense that um you know you you you
they're there certain performing and
they're not all kind of like interacting
well together
and I'm wondering on on a global level
if if the same holds true in the sense
that there will be kind of like fizzle
which you know will trade more with each
other and in which perhaps like a lot of
employers will move and and will kind of
entice their employees to move into and
that won't be the same parts in which
they have previously been living but
what that may mean on a geopolitical
level I mean we see a lot of Alliance
shifting already right we see the
Italy's curve finally starting to
flatten was wind China came in and gave
it a bunch of aid which included
surveillance drones and other things so
and you see EU and EU adjacent countries
thinking that he would support them in
didn't and then getting Chinese support
or a few cases some other types of
support so massive alliance shifting we
see even within the US the groups of
states that are clustering so the the
California Oregon Washington com
flex and the seven state complex around
New York and I really feel that the u.s.
getting its shit together and being able
to help lead Alliance efforts is pretty
critical and will make a big difference
to the way the world plays out and
because even though I can't say the u.s.
is actually a republic it at least it at
least has that vague idea of having some
values or ideals around a republic or
around democracy whereas when we look at
China and we look at Russia and we look
at Saudi Arabia and we look at Iran and
most of the other power players they
don't even this like autocracy is really
fully embraced and I don't think
exponential tech empowered autocracy is
a world we want to go towards and I
think that if those are the players that
are offering aid to the rest of the
world and the US isn't because the u.s.
is so internally fighting over its own
power because it has and this is how big
empires die right and democracies make
it two to three hundred years and we're
almost at 250 years there's so much
power here that you have so much
internal infighting to see who gets that
power that you just kind of lose
awareness on what's actually happening
in the world and that you're losing
relative position to it and it's not
that I want the u.s. is positioned
relative to the world to be something in
particular but I think that its ability
to help participate with alliance
efforts for the values of roughly
democratic type Western civilization
values having a place I think is super
important and it's one of the things
that I most want to see people engaged
in is efforts that decrease internal by
partisan warfare and create more a more
effective national governance that can
then do International Alliance building
better thank you okay we have two more
questions from Luke Nozick and from Josh
about you coming to meet you so Daniel
you had yet said I'm not certified to
miss her - I think it's
comments something about empowering
people or distributing power and and
then you recently alluded to Republic or
democracy in these things being good um
can you be more specific about what the
the the problem is with power and who
should yeah who should actually organize
it so that we could do things
effectively like do international treats
because it doesn't seem like you know
warring parties in a democracy is send
somebody I'm doing it that's very
obvious but what do you specifically
believe about how to organize power we
should have it and so that you can
effectively have a big question
um could go in a bunch of directions do
you mean like do I think moving towards
a positive global Singleton is what we
should aim for or is there some kind of
future of democracy that we should aim
for or like how do we make America
better currently and obviously when we
talk about power there's power in the
markets which is achieved a certain way
power in the state power and religion
and culture yeah I I would like to be
able to address where the question what
you're interested in better
can't hear you currently I think Allison
you have to unmute him I mean
[Music]
you're unmuted for half a second i muted
there we go there you go again I'd like
you to be as idealistic as possible so
none of this triage you know or
incrementalism stuff just what do you
think is possible for for humans in an
ideal state I'm not trying to get a
sense of looking at what your ideal you
know political or social organization is
I've got it and actually think all of
those different realms are quite
important because they there's they're
sort of orthogonal ways of looking at at
the whole thing some some governments
can be structures that it's there's
there's one that's autocratic over the
other ones but many times we have them
overlapping in empowering that religious
power concurrent with you the Catholic
Church and yet all the kings in the in
the Middle Ages concurring forget the
witness system yeah I think the
distribution of power between those
different types of institutions was
actually a problematic and important and
because early became progressively more
problematic but like when you think
about in the u.s. the separation of the
state and the market why we didn't just
have a pure libertarian model we had the
idea of a kind of liberal democracy but
also the separation of a state and a
church then we say liberal democracy and
kind of leave the role of the church out
and mostly focus on market and and state
and yet interestingly you read all of
the founding father comments about the
need for people to have some kind of
moral education as well as a you know
formal civic education for anything like
democratic process to work the way I
think about that and I'll mention the
longer term one the way I think about
that briefly is
the reason that a state was put in place
in this in the kind of us experiment
was it was seen that markets could solve
most problems or solve a lot of the
problems in terms of innovation and
efficiency but that they also would lead
to organized crime and they would lead
to tragedy of the Commons and different
types of places where it was
incentivized to do things it really
created a shitty quality of life for
everyone so there was an idea that there
was to be a state that had some kind of
ability to regulate the most predatory
aspects of markets and so there was this
idea of law and a monopoly of violence
to be able to institute law that was
based on jurisprudence which is based on
ethics and which is why the founding
documents are kind of existential
ethical documents and that's actually
where the role of the church came in
which was we didn't want a single Church
having dominion over that but the idea
that there was Phyllis ah the church and
the Academy and that there were deep
considerations of what is a good life
that is informing ethics it's informing
jurisprudence it's informing law to be
able to bind the predatory aspects of
markets will facilitate the helpful
aspects of markets simultaneously and
kind of the way I see it is that the
markets the predatory aspects were
designed to be bound by the state but
the state was designed to be bound by a
educated and engaged populace and where
the state was of foreign by the people
and otherwise you get the watchdog issue
where you have maximum incentive for the
market forces to capture the regulatory
forces and then just get crony
capitalism but in order for and then the
people are actually bound by the market
which means accounting that they can't
ask for rights they aren't willing to
take responsibilities for and they can't
you know implement shit where the where
the accounting doesn't work out and if
you kind of think of that there's a
really nice balance in it but it's easy
to see how a symmetries of power emerged
where even though there's aggregate
symmetry between supply side and demands
there's more coordination on supply-side
than there is undemanding asymmetric
information Warfare's that lead to a
less educated ant+ just natural human
weakness at scale that lead to the
population not checking the government
and then the state force the market
forces capturing it
so I think there's some stuff that can
be done to actually reverse this
institutional decay and make a better
version of this thing and I'm actually
very interested in that I don't think it
meets the sufficiency criteria long term
and so then the question of what is a
more visionary long term distribution of
power and choice making look like I can
say that I don't know because we haven't
implemented it and the ideas that I have
about it I don't know if will work but I
hit I have thoughts on this topic that
have to do with one of the ways that I
frame it up if you think about if you
think about kind of Jeffery West's
analysis and scale and the
correspondence of that with kind of
Dunbar society limits and the idea that
in general intended groups of people
whether they're companies or countries
get diminishing collective intelligence
and productive capacity at scale beyond
give or take in evolutionary tribal size
then that ends up creating a basis for
smaller groups to be more intelligent
relative to the larger group and you
both have an incentive for defection and
the capacity to defect and get away with
it because the larger group becomes
stupider and can't do the appropriate
accounting so you end up getting niches
for sociopathic predatory behavior on
this system whereas if you had linear
development or super linear development
of collective intelligence as a function
of scale as you go above Dunbar number
you could have the group be smart enough
to actually notice and bind the
sociopathic defections where everyone
would do better by being by
participating with the collective
intelligence system and defecting
against it now exactly how do we
instantiate that I again I think that
goes it's conversation I would love to
have a conversation I'd love to have
with you that takes a much longer chunk
of time okay I realize the line of
questions is just starting to ramp up
[Music]
then you would be able to say for one
more question then we headed out sure
yeah okay yeah sure maybe you do one
more question and then maybe Luke and
Daniel I can convince both of you to
come on and talk it out on the next one
together okay
yes sir I'll search for you yes
okay I'm me to you now thank you good
evening
Thank You Daniel this was amazing it was
a very right range I think that the how
to find the best system question seems
to come down to something that might be
eventually contradictory like how can we
combine the benefits of competent
totalitarianism with the robustness and
self-actualization and non-violence of a
well entrenched democracy and it's a on
top of a very diverse and tourist
population and society and cultural
traditions that's so that is a super
difficult question and probably won't be
able to solve it tonight so a very
simple question maybe in the end what
would happen if you take the present
situation where the FDA is blocking
testing and together with the CDC and
some other institutions more or less
directly responsible for the deaths of
something like loss of 90,000 Americans
and with an X F website and how can we
solve that in the situation consequent
walking the FDA what would happen if
California for instance works the FDA
and the federal agencies will look very
firmly at us but at the moment the
situation seems to be a weakness of the
federal government that would allow ago
she ate the destitution between federal
and local power and create
- segments
yeah I I will also say I don't know the
answer to this would need to look in it
more depth but a few thoughts that come
to mind
I think states can do totally fucked up
stuff and have people who are very power
seeking at the level states even at the
level of cities but they don't have like
states don't have nukes
even though nukes might live in a state
the federal government does they don't
states have a National Guard but they
don't have weapons of mass destruction
and they don't have the same types of
massive power consolidation so I think
the Tenth Amendment is very important
and I think the movements to an
increased Tim's like when we talk about
things that could get worse or better
right now in the US the idea that states
become more relevant is actually a
possibly very good idea whit while
having the factor for right and left
states moving in further apart
directions and increased tension between
them so we we have to factor for that
but that's mostly engineered that's
mostly narrative or fair engineered and
could be addressed but I do think taking
it beyond the state down to the city
level is better because cities are real
things and states are fictions just like
nation states are fictions like where
the boundary is is we've determined in a
war or a trade or whatever but cities
are based on the actual goods and
services and transportation dynamics
that need to be within a particular
space of each other so I think and this
is what Jeffrey West was showing and
scale was that cities actually do have
productive capacity that can be linear
or super linear as a function of
population so I think having more
governance at the level of cities is
very interesting and then having
coalition's of cities network network
dynamics between cities cities and the
surrounding metropolitan areas pretty
much defined by transportation dynamics
and there are obviously also tricky
things we're like let's say we're
dealing with a pandemic where let's say
an area closes off its border and
figures out how to become a Green Zone
but the other areas adjacent to it don't
well it doesn't actually get to reopen
its border and re-issue life without the
other areas doing that or you know one
person can cause the infections again so
this is a place where the
rights of individual places and their
responsibilities to each other are just
so profoundly connected which is why
this is such a big deal I think one I
think there's some stuff that's fucked
up about the way tests have been blocked
and rolled out I think I think there's a
lot about it but I also think that
there's a lot that's really bad about
the tests like I don't think the
immunoassays are useful for tests and
trace or really diagnosis for
suppression at all there it takes too
many days from the time you were exposed
and are infectious for the antibodies to
show up and the even even if you have
one that had very low false negatives at
that point and then there's too much
that isn't known about what the
antibodies actually mean yet or how long
they last or the decay rate on them or
any of those things so I think we would
need high sensitivity pcr that could be
very very widely utilized to be able to
have testing really become very
meaningful as a suppression strategy and
so we're not waiting for antibody
response in the blood we're being able
to detect presence of the virus in the
mucosa so you know nasal and oral swabs
and I think
I think we could roll out specific areas
could roll out those types of
diagnostics and be able to show the
effectiveness of it mostly commercially
and with local governments participation
and I think if it showed enough
effectiveness so like we're talking with
some people in Las Vegas because Las
Vegas is very focused on reopening
because they're losing like a billion
dollars a week per casino or whatever
staying closed so they really want to
reopen but Vegas by itself reopening
could cause the infection to never go in
the world because people come from all
over touch everything together in a
closed air environment it circulated air
and then fly back to the rest of the
world but they also have all the money
to actually do the thing properly and
the local government gets enough money
from them they want to really
participate so they could roll out HEPA
filters and pecco filters and nanotech
surface treatments and detection
mechanisms and get the security on them
right and and point-of-contact rapid
turnaround pcr Diagnostics and actually
be able to invest the capital to show
the effectiveness to then be able to
lower the economies of scale and the
questions of if it's true or not to then
get them implemented other places so I'm
interested in some of those approaches
thank you so much for joining today I
mean intended so bye bye everyone see
you tomorrow Thank You Daniel